A Guide to the Additional Papers of Alan Cheuse, 1961-1988
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Additional Papers of Alan Cheuse 1961-1988
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
10726-c,-d
This collection consists of 945 items (10 Hollinger boxes; 3 linear shelf feet).
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Aceess restrictions may apply to specific student records under the terms of the Family Educational Rights and Privacy Act (F.E.R.P.A.).
Acquisition Information
Alan Cheuse of Fairfax, Virginia, placed his papers on loan to the Library on June 3, 1988. The papers were purchased by the Library on September 11, 2003.
Scope and Content Information
This addition to the papers of Alan Cheuse consists of 945 items (10 Hollinger boxes; 3 linear shelf feet), 1961-1988, and includes correspondence; drafts of his novels, The Bohemians, Fall Out of Heaven, and The Grandmothers' Club, and various other short stories, reviews, and articles; newsclippings and printed material; photographs; cassette tape recordings; and topical files.
The first series in this collection consists of the typed manuscripts and proofs of three of Cheuse's novels, The Bohemians, Fall Out of Heaven, and The Grandmothers' Club. The second series contains Cheuse's reviews of books, articles, and short stories, both in draft and printed form. A complete listing of these can be found in the folder listing at the end of this guide on pages six and seven.
Correspondence comprises the third series of these papers. Cheuse's general correspondence files include much personal correspondence, correspondence with his publisher Gibbs M. Smith, Inc., and correspondence with the editors of magazines such as Horizon, USA Today, Ms., TV Guide, The Atlantic Monthly, The Boston Globe, The Paris Review, The Antioch Review, and The Texas Review.
Individual correspondents include: T. Alan Broughton (1984 Sep 17); Robert Olen Butler (1988 Jul 28); Nicholas Delbanco (1988 Jun 21); Digby Diehl (1988 Jul 7 & n.d.); E.L. Doctorow (1985 Nov 27); Robert Draper (1986 Apr 19); Richard Ford (1985 Oct 10, Dec 11; 1986 Mar 3 & 15; 1987 Oct 5); John Gardner (see Liz Darhansoff file, 1981 Jun 11); Gail Godwin (1986 Jan 17 & Mar 24); Herbert Gold (1985 Sep 7 & Dec 6); Ben Greer (1985 Dec 12); James D. Houston (1987 Nov 10); Josephine Humphreys (1985 Sep 28, Oct [12], Nov 24; 1986 Jan 16; 1987 Nov 29;); John Irving (1988 Jul 19); Jim Lehrer (1988 Jun 21); Cynthia MacDonald (1986 Apr 15); Terry Mcmillan (1988 Jul 14); John Magilavy (1984 Oct 7); Bernard Malamud (1985 Oct 22 & Dec 19); Mitch Markowitz (1985 Dec 5; 1988 Feb 10, Jul 14); Wright Morris (1985 Nov 18); Peter Taylor (1988 Jul 18); Richard Tillinghast (1987 Jun 1); Tobias Wolff (1985 Dec 6); and Al Young (1987 Sep 25).
There are also four separate folders which include early letters from Alan Cheuse to his friends, Robert Pinsky and Peter Najarian, Apple-wood Books and its editor, Phil Zuckerman, The New Yorker and Fran Kiernan, and his literary agent, Liz Darhansoff.
Cheuse's early letters to Pinsky and Narjarian, 1961-1967, include: his conception of the vocation of writing, and his stay in Spain (1961 Nov 4); his United States Army draft concerns, plans to visit Greece, Yugoslavia, and Morocco, and his "Spanish Dame" story (1961 Nov 13); a description of a group of short stories that he wants to write based on his experiences in Europe (1961 Dec 19); mention of his marriage to Meme (1964 Sep 29); a discussion of Norman Mailer's book, The Naked and the Dead(1965 Nov 23); comments about the Butler Institute, Guadalajara, Mexico (1965 Oct 6, Nov 23; 1966 Mar 15); and his work for the Welfare Department of New York City (1966 Dec 11; 1967 Mar 7).
Correspondence with Liz Darhansoff contains much correspondence concerning her attempts to place Cheuse's novel about John Reed with a publisher, and editorial comments about "Rabbi Guatemala" by Caroline Sutton (1980 Jan 12), Faith Sale (1981 Apr 28), and a very detailed analysis by John Gardner (1981 Jun 11).
Correspondence with Fran Kiernan of The New Yorker contains her criticism of several of Alan Cheuse's short stories. These include: "Fishing for Coyote," "Book of Life & the Book of Death," "Incidents of Travel in the Yucatan," "Care," "Accident," "Quest for Ambrose Bierce," "The Buzzer Box," "Garden of the Gods," "Land of the Lost," "Kismet," "Toward Easter Island," "Slides," and "On the Tram."
The last series consists of miscellaneous papers, topical files, and cassette tapes, which are listed at the end of the guide.
Organization
This collection is arranged in four series: I) Manuscripts of Books (Boxes 1-5) II) Short Stories, Articles, and Book Reviews (Box 6) III) Correspondence (Boxes 7-9) IV) Miscellaneous (Box 10).
Contents List
- SERIES I: MANUSCRIPTS OF BOOKS
  - The Bohemians(3 folders) ca. 1982, TMsS (Box 1)
  - The Bohemians- Second Version (2 folders) ca. 1982, TMsS (Box 1)
  - The Bohemians- Second Version ca. 1982, TMsS (Box 2)
  - The Bohemians- Final Proof, Kraft, with corrections (2 folders) ca. 1982, TMs (Box 2)
  - Fall Out of Heaven- Original Manuscript (electrostatic copy) by Philip K. Cheuse (2 folders) [ante 1983], TMs (Box 2)
  - Fall Out of Heaven- Early Version (4 folders) ca. 1986-1987, TMs (Box 3)
  - Fall Out of Heaven, with Dust Jacket 1987, Uncorrected Page Proof (Box 3)
  - The Grandmothers' Club- Early Version entitled "Rabbi Guatemala" (3 folders) [ca. 1986], TMsS (Box 4)
  - The Grandmothers' Club(2 folders) ca. 1986, TMs (Box 4)
  - The Grandmothers' Club(2 folders) [ca. 1986], TMsS (Box 5)
  - The Grandmothers' Club- Computer Printout Version (2 folders) [ca. 1986], TMs (Box 5)
  - The Grandmothers' Club, signed by Alan Cheuse 1986, Blue Line Proof (Box 5)
- SERIES II: SHORT STORIES, ARTICLES, & BOOK REVIEWS
  - "The Book of Life and the Book of Death" (2 Copies) ca. 1978-1988, TMs (Box 6)
  - "Books in flames: a view of Latin American literature" in The Antioch Review1978 Spring, Print (Box 6)
  - "The Boone Tavern Hotel" n.d., TMs (Box 6)
  - Boston Globe Magazine Articles 1978-1983, Print (Box 6)
  - "Death Comes Up for Tenure" (incomplete) n.d., TMs (Box 6)
  - "Evasion" n.d., TMs (Box 6)
  - "A Fair of the Heart" 1984 Jun 3, Print (Box 6)
  - "A Father's Going" n.d., TMs (Box 6)
  - "Fifty Meters Out" n.d., TMs (Box 6)
  - "Garden City of the West" from "John Reed: A Novel," later published as The Bohemians1979 Jun, TMs (Box 6)
  - "Hamlet in Haiti: Style in Carpentier's The Kingdom of This World" in Caribbean Quarterly1975 Dec, Print (Box 6)
  - "How I Learned to Accept Helping Around the House" n.d., Print (Box 6)
  - "The Inca Wall" in Review 25/261980, Print (Box 6)
  - "It's Like Coming Home for Thanksgiving" in TV Guide1980 Nov 15, Print (Box 6)
  - "Kismet" in Bennington Review1984 Spring, Print (Box 6)
  - "Land of Cotton" n.d., TMs (Box 6)
  - "The Lost Books" in Review1976 Fall, Print (Box 6)
  - "Mario Vargas Llosa and Conversation in The Cathedral: The Question of Naturalism" 1977 & 1978, Print (Box 6)
  - "News from Knoxville" n.d., TMs (Box 6)
  - "Nights on the Cumberland Plateau" (First Version) n.d., TMs (Box 6)
  - "The Quest for Ambrose Bierce" in The Black Warrior Review1980, Print (Box 6)
  - "The Quest for Ambrose Bierce" in Graywolf Annual Four: Stories by Men1987 Dec, Galley Proof (Box 6)
  - Reviews 1981-1988, TMs & Print (Box 6)
  - Reviews - Unpublished 1977, TMs (Box 6)
  - "Sentences" n.d., TMs (Box 6)
  - ["Spanish Dames Have No Hips"] n.d., TMs (Box 6)
  - "Tennessee Blues" n.d., TMs (Box 6)
  - "Way Out West: The Exploratory Fiction of Ronald Sukenick" 1978, Print (Box 6)
  - "Writing at Sewanee" n.d., TMs (Box 6)
  - "Writing Short Fiction" - A Transcript of the Austin Workshop 1987 Oct 24, TMs (Box 6)
- SERIES III: CORRESPONDENCE
  - Correspondence (8 folders) 1980-1987 Sep (Box 7)
  - Correspondence (7 folders) 1987 Oct-1988 Aug, & n.d. (Box 8)
  - Letters from Alan Cheuse to Robert Pinsky & Peter Najarian 1961-1967 (Box 9)
  - Correspondence - Apple-wood Books and Phil Zuckerman 1978-1983, n.d. (Box 9)
  - Correspondence - Liz Darhansoff 1977-1981 (Box 9)
  - Correspondence - The New Yorker1979-1982 (Box 9)
- SERIES IV: MISCELLANEOUS
  - American Book Awards 1984 (Box 10)
  - Austin Writers' League Workshop 1987 Oct-Nov (Box 10)
  - Aztlan Writers of the American Southwest 1981 & n.d. (Box 10)
  - Class Papers re "The Seals" by Alan Cheuse from Dr. Keaney's English 556 Class 1988 Apr (Box 10)
  - Criticism re The Bohemiansn.d. (Box 10)
  - Energy Notes n.d. (Box 10)
  - Financial & Legal Papers 1980-1987 (Box 10)
  - Grant Applications 1982-1983, 1987 (Box 10)
  - Miscellaneous Papers 1980-1988 (Box 10)
  - Notes re "Rabbi Guatemala," including newsclippings n.d. (Box 10)
  - Peter Matthiessen Essay n.d. (Box 10)
  - Printed Material 1980, 1984-1986 (Box 10)
  - Proposals for Articles 1979, n.d. (Box 10)
  - Publicity 1980-1988, n.d. (Box 10)
  - Royalty Statements 1980-1983 (Box 10)
  - Short Story Markets n.d. (Box 10)
  - Short Story Symposium, Detroit Public Library 1985 Apr 19-20 (Box 10)
  - Student Papers 1977, n.d. (Box 10)
  - Tennessee 1980-1981, n.d. (Box 10)
- TAPE RECORDINGS
  - Alan Cheuse reading the beginning of The Grandmothers' Club and Mary Robison reading her short story, "Trying," at Bennington College, Bennington, Vermont (T-878) 1986 Jul 25 (Box 10)
  - Alan Cheuse reading his first published work, "Fishing for Coyote," and his latest published work, the ending of The Grandmothers' Club, at The Book Gallery, near the University of Virginia, with an introduction by Darcey Steinke (T-879) 1987 Feb 1 (Box 10)
  - Alan Cheuse reading from his latest book, Fall Out of Heaven, at the Williams Corner Bookstore, Charlottesville, Virginia, with an introduction by George Garrett. He begins with the story of his trip to the Soviet Union. (T-880) 1987 Sep 16 (Box 10)